Toni WahrstŠtter: Hello!
Pooja Ranjan: Hey, Tony!
Toni WahrstŠtter: How's it going?
Pooja Ranjan: Good, good.
Pooja Ranjan: So I hope, É
Pooja Ranjan: Everything should be good. I'm open to stream on both platforms, X and YouTube. Just let me know whenever you want to move over the stream, because I'll be pre-streaming in about 2 minutes.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, perfect. Yeah, I think we will wait a few more minutes anyway, and then I will just tell you to start the stream.
Pooja Ranjan: Sure, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Cool, thank you.
Barnabas: You knowÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Hello.
Toni WahrstŠtter: GM, GM, let's wait a few more minutes.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I think we're good to start the stream now.
Pooja Ranjan: We are life.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Thank you very much.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Hello, everyone, and welcome to the first, EOP7928 breakout call.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I thought it makes sense, to have a breaker call around the EAP, now on a more regular basis, just to keep track of progress happening.
Toni WahrstŠtter: On today's agenda, there's not that many topics, but we still have, some open points to discuss, and I would propose that we start, today's first breakout with Jared talking a bit about the implementation progress he made in GEF,
Toni WahrstŠtter: Then there is Rahul, who will talk a little bit about testing progress and everything that is happening on the testing front.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And then we have Chen from the EVE storage team for QuarkChain, who will present some results on their performance analysis of block-level access lists in GAF.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And before we start getting into those topics, let me just quickly recap some info around the EAP.
Toni WahrstŠtter: First of all, on blockaccesslist.xyz, I posted it into the chat.
Toni WahrstŠtter: You should find all the important information, especially if you scroll down to the resources headline.
Toni WahrstŠtter: There you find all the, specs, like the EL specs, the execution API specs, and the CL specs, as well as test cases and everything. So this is kind of the place where we try to bundle all that information.
Toni WahrstŠtter: AndÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, everything is summarized there. If you want to submit new test cases, then Rahul will show you how to do so. There's a dedicated testing doc where we collect many test cases.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But yeah, without further ado, I would say, Jared would beÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: pass it to you in order for you to present us some initial results you collected on GAF.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, cool. Yeah, so I can justÉ just to summarize where the Geth implementation is at right now, we fully implemented the SIP, except for storage and account reads,
Jared Wasinger: É So, basically, at this point, É we'reÉ
Jared Wasinger: we're more or less ready toÉ toÉ to do a DevNet, in the sense that the code is written and I'm reasonably sure.
Jared Wasinger: that the consensus API, the engine API changes and the minor changes should work, but I'm still verifying that on my end.
Jared Wasinger: The executionÉ theÉ so, block access list execution and, building areÉ areÉ are implemented.
Jared Wasinger: And I've doneÉ quite a bit of work to get the performance To a reasonable, É point.
Jared Wasinger: So, I guess I'll just share my screen. I have a few slides just kind of summarizing
Jared Wasinger: The latest benchmark.
Jared Wasinger: WhereÉ used to Google Meet, so, É
Jared Wasinger: Okay, so I'm just going toÉ
Jared Wasinger: Looks like I have to give it a permission here.
Jared Wasinger: I have to rejoin the call.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Karim, I think this is a good point, regarding the reads, I think this is still up for discussion. So far, my feeling was that, the majority of people is still for including the reads, just because parallel
Toni WahrstŠtter: I.O. might, be very valuable, especially with bigger blocks.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But, yeah, this is still something we have to discuss.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, Jared is back.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Jared, are youÉ are you already talking?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Is this true?
Milos: You're muted.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Jared, can you hear us? You're still muted.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, yeah, yeah, oops, okay. Yeah, so, just to, É
Jared Wasinger: overview of the serial execution that Geth currently performs. We execute transactions one after the other. Simultaneously, for mutated state, we will fetch
Jared Wasinger: Intermediate trinodes in the background, so that when we go to compute the state root, It'sÉ vast, É
Jared Wasinger: Oop, this is the wrong slide. Oops.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, that's the next slide.
Jared Wasinger: Okay, soÉ
Jared Wasinger: MmmÉ right, in block execution, compute the state rehash, we validate block fields and the state rehash against what's reported in the block, and then we write the mutated state to disk.
Jared Wasinger: Block access list execution, parallelizes the transaction execution and the state route calculation. So in this model.
Jared Wasinger: WeÉ
Jared Wasinger: Don't have the advantage of being able to prefetch trinodes in the background, but when we go to commit, we can do everything inÉ we can commit all of the nodes, or when we go to compute the tri-root hash, and we have to fetch the intermediate tri nodes, we can do this all in parallel.
Jared Wasinger: So, it ends up being not a huge performance hit, É
Jared Wasinger: So when we executeÉ when we execute transactions and simultaneously calculate the state route.
Jared Wasinger: We provide an empty pre-state to theÉ to these, like, worker threads.
Jared Wasinger: And then they will, buildÉ they will, É
Jared Wasinger: So they will sort of, like, É
Jared Wasinger: compute the state they need to execute against by looking at the access list. And then some of that information is also supplemented from theÉ
Jared Wasinger: from disk.
Jared Wasinger: Block excess construction, yeah, like I mentioned, we haven't implemented reads. I wasÉ
Jared Wasinger: kind of under the impression we would remove them. It sounds like we'll talk about this today. For rights, weÉ it's pretty straightforward when we goÉ weÉ weÉ yeah, it's pretty straightforward.
Jared Wasinger: Alright, so, can you all see my mouse?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yes.
Jared Wasinger: Okay. SoÉ The performance of the master branch isÉ
Jared Wasinger: the overhead is dominated by the stateÉ by the execution. So these first three columns, these first three rows.
Jared Wasinger: areÉ if you sum them together, this is the time it takes to perform the execution. SoÉ
Jared Wasinger: So then when we go to update, theÉ
Jared Wasinger: The account update here, and then the storage update here are fairly quick, because we have pre-warmed trinodes while executing transactions. But the actual transaction execution time isÉ is large.
Jared Wasinger: Oh, I should also mention, so thisÉ these numbers I'm giving are a benchmark of an import of 10,000 blocks.
Jared Wasinger: It's not a hugeÉ
Jared Wasinger: span of time, and I'm running a longer benchmark now, so I will have some updated numbers soon, but right now, this is what I have to present. SoÉ
Jared Wasinger: Right, so with the BAL branch, on this, on this benchmark, The, É so the performancesÉ
Jared Wasinger: Overall, the block processing speed's about 2.6 times faster.
Jared Wasinger: So the state root calculation here is ourÉ our slowest, but the block executionÉ
Jared Wasinger: is, very fast. É And then, so theseÉ theseÉ these block preprocessing isÉ isÉ
Jared Wasinger: we can kind of ignore that, because that's justÉ this is aÉ this branch was a work in progress when I performed these benchmarks, but I think that this step
Jared Wasinger: This step, and thisÉ the preprocessing state loading is actually just a component of the preprocessing step, so it's not, like, an additiveÉ
Jared Wasinger: You don't add all these up to get the total, the total time it took to process the block.
Jared Wasinger: But I think that this step actually can be optimized away, and I'll be working on that at some point over the next week or two.
Jared Wasinger: É
Jared Wasinger: Right, so, I mean, yeah, this is kind of what I have right now, and I think thatÉ
Jared Wasinger: I've been doing someÉ I've been running a longer benchmark, and there are definitelyÉ É
Jared Wasinger: spikes. So here, the execution is, like, fairly reasonable, but I've definitely seen some spikes where the execution is actually, in general.
Jared Wasinger: on par with the state root calculation, so far as what I'm seeing.
Jared Wasinger: É And yeah, so I will be continuing to benchmark this and try to improve it, É
Jared Wasinger: I think right now, though, from what I've seen with the latest results, I think at least a 2.2X or slowÉ or 2.2X or so speed up
Jared Wasinger: seems to hold, and É I mean, I'll have to run more benchmarks to actually see what the master branch performs over this longer period of time that I'm measuring, butÉ
Jared Wasinger: Yeah.
Jared Wasinger: So that'sÉ TheÉ yeah, that's pretty much my update.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Awesome, thanks.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Just a quick question, in thisÉ when you say execution, and you didn't do any parallel I.O. in this model, right? Because you said you were not using the reads yet, or the state locations.
Jared Wasinger: Well, so the I.O. is parallel because you'reÉ
Jared Wasinger: it's allÉ they're executing in parallel, so I think, like, a good portion of the speedup is actually due to the parallel I.O, É
Jared Wasinger: But, yeah, it'sÉ it's not executing with the reads, and also, É
Jared Wasinger: I mean, I canÉ I can definitely measure reads. ItÉ itÉ itÉ
Jared Wasinger: it's doable. It kind of involves adding a separate component, butÉ It can be done.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Right.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, this also plays into this, what Kareem is saying in the chat.
Jared Wasinger: items.
Toni WahrstŠtter: the state locations, then you can do something like batch parallel I.O,
Toni WahrstŠtter: But if you don't have the read locations, then you can still do some parallel I.O, because you already parallelized the transactions.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, just to answer this question, so I don'tÉ
Jared Wasinger: I don't think we need to do batchÉ
Jared Wasinger: I don'tÉ I'm not exactly sure what this question is, but I don't think that we need to do batch I.O. up front. I think we can just start executing
Jared Wasinger: Like, we don't need the pre-state completely loaded.
Jared Wasinger: at the start, if that's what this question is getting at, right? We can just start executing, and then load things in as we need them.
Jared Wasinger: É
Jared Wasinger: And with theÉ yeah, I mean, with the reads also, it's like, it doesn't really make senseÉ because they're not indexed by theÉ by where they occur in the block, I think that parallelizing loading them up front would actually beÉ
Jared Wasinger: I think it would be slower, personally.
Jared Wasinger: É.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Right. Yeah, this is a good argument. And then the question becomesÉ If we don'tÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: Put the state locations in there, because they give us someÉ certain amount of speedup.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Are there other reasons why we keep them in?
Toni WahrstŠtter: And one of the reasons could be that
Toni WahrstŠtter: We just, have more information in the block lab access list.
Toni WahrstŠtter: We don't only have the information that
Toni WahrstŠtter: changed. We know what changed, and in which way it changed, or to what it changed.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And then we will also know, like, what was accessed.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, definitely. I would say, in that case, it would beÉ
Jared Wasinger: I wonder if itÉ if thereÉ what the usefulness trade-off is. Like, if there's noÉ if there's information that storage slots were accessed in a block, but we don't know what transaction they were accessed inÉ
Jared Wasinger: É IÉ I'mÉ I guess I'm just wondering how that would be used.
Jared Wasinger: ButÉ.
Po: Okay, soÉ.
Jared Wasinger: But to answer the question, batch loadÉ
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, I mean, I can measure it. IÉ IÉ
Jared Wasinger: We alreadyÉ in the benchmarks I presented, there is actually some batch loading up front of the pre-state that gets modified, and itÉ it adds
Jared Wasinger: I mean, maybe, like, 10% overhead overall, soÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Cool, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, Chen, did you want to say something, or do you want to, just continue with presenting, the work you guys did?
Po: Yeah, actually, when we are doing the benchmark, andÉ
Po: We have aÉ we use some of theÉ É
Po: account and storage slot, use this information to doÉ with this information, we can do some kind of, É
Po: This snapshot and, to accelerate theÉ
Po: block process as a queuing time. I, I don't know if IÉ
Po: I expressed my opinion correctly, yeah, becauseÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, so you, you say, the state locations would also be helpful for execution.
Po: Yeah, yeah, because, there are two options. One is, like Jared did.
Po: You've fetched the storage and account state during execution.
Po: Yeah, the second option is you'll just prefetch all the pre-blocks state, then executing, yeah. TheÉ
Po: Benefits of the, É Prefetching the state is that you can do some
Po: Snapshot, because we know all theÉ Free.
Po: post-financial state. This, state, we can, kind of, do multi-layer stated reading.
Po: Yeah, we can snapshot everyÉ about, for example, 10 transactions, and then we canÉ
Po: make, this snapshot. Yeah, if we want to adjust the state, we could, just, ButÉ
Po: Do a kind of a multi-layer reading, yeah.
Po: And this will accelerate the, state rate, state rate.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, is thatÉ is that part of theÉ of the benchmark as you're going to present?
Po: Yeah, it's part of the result, but I didn't, writeÉ presented the routine on my presentation, yeah.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, no worry.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, yeah, it would beÉ would be nice if you couldÉ if you could share, those results withÉ with this group.
Toni WahrstŠtter: would be very interesting to look into those, because I think you also did some analysis onÉ É
Toni WahrstŠtter: what happens if we 10x the block size, right? If we have suddenly, like, 10x the gas limit?
Toni WahrstŠtter: How would that impact execution time versus I.O. time?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect, I see you posted it into the chat.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Great.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, I agree with Carl. I think we shouldÉ we should get some better benchmarks onÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: what do we actually get fromÉ from Batch.io?
Jared Wasinger: Hey, Poe, I have a quick question about this, this, slide you just posted. So the speed up at the bottom, is that, versus master, or whatÉ what is thatÉ what is that based on?
Po: Let me rephrase your question. You mean master is the main branch of gas?
Jared Wasinger: Yeah.
Po: Yeah, yeah, theÉ Version is, É
Po: Yeah, in the second PPT is 1.16É it's, close to the latest version. The latest version is 1.1716.2, and, my version is 1.16.1, yeah.
Jared Wasinger: Gotcha, okay.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Okay, and if I interpret it correctly, it's like the result is also like a 2X speedup, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: For average cases, right?
Po: Yeah, right.
Carl Beekhuizen: I mean, I wanna just highlight again that we care about worst case, which is a 33x speedup, supposedly.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Right, yeah, that's a good point, because if you use, like, 32 cores, likeÉ As this experiment did.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And we would have had, like, worst-case blocks than, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: We would have gotten a 32X speedup, this isÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: But even, even for the average case, like, a 2X sounds already, like, more than I expected. Of course, I expected, like, big, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: And performance improvement for worst cases.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But, like, 2x4 average cases is already, like, very good.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But yeah, it would be interesting to find out, like, if clients actually need the state locations to do something like batch I.O. up front.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Or if we remove them, andÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: In the end, it's not only do clients need them, but do, É Should the protocol have them?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Maybe there are some use cases we're not aware of yet.
Toni WahrstŠtter: That might need them.
Carl Beekhuizen: And we also need to weigh that off against theÉ
Carl Beekhuizen: Like, cost and time of sending that over the wire.
Carl Beekhuizen: You know, they're notÉ they're not free toÉ to add, or, sorry, to have.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Right.
Jared Wasinger: It's also possible that if we can batch the storage lookups
Jared Wasinger: so for red storage and red accounts, if we can do that up front, but alsoÉ but kick that off after we've started performing the state root calculation, I mean, I couldÉ
Jared Wasinger: I could see that being an interestingÉ route to benchmark and Explore.
Carl Beekhuizen: Can you say a little bit more about what you mean by after the stated computation?
Jared Wasinger: So, theÉ If weÉ if we batch load
Jared Wasinger: non-mutated storage slots and accounts up front, but we haven't yet, started to compute the state root calculation. We'reÉ
Jared Wasinger: Adding overhead up front and delaying work we could already do.
Jared Wasinger: Because, like, the mutated storage slots and accounts aren't needed toÉ you don't need to load them to compute the state root.
Carl Beekhuizen: Okay, I'mÉ Not following here, like, don't we need the post date?
Carl Beekhuizen: Like, that the root of the post state at the end of the block?
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, sure. I thought we were talking about the, like, when we say batchÉ IÉ batchÉ
Jared Wasinger: I.O. up front here atÉ
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, I'm justÉ I'm just saying, like, if weÉ we can, of course, batch the loading of the mutated accounts up front. That's the only, like, precursorÉ the mutated accounts and the mutated store slots up front, because that's the only precursor for performing the state root update, but thenÉ
Jared Wasinger: É But we wouldn't also need to warm theÉ É
Jared Wasinger: Any storage slots or accounts that aren't mutated?
Jared Wasinger: BeforeÉ before we, in parallel, start the root computation.
Carl Beekhuizen: Yeah, I see.
Jared Wasinger: I'm kind of just thinking aloud here, butÉ.
Carl Beekhuizen: Yeah, yeah.
Carl Beekhuizen: I mean, I thinkÉ I think a lot of the thought process comes back toÉ like, Dunkard did some experiments a while ago, just on, like, batch random reads.
Carl Beekhuizen: I'm also very contrived.
Carl Beekhuizen: Example, but he got something stupid, like a 50x speedup.
Carl Beekhuizen: onÉ Floating arbitrary.
Carl Beekhuizen: data from an SSD.
Carl Beekhuizen: Just by doing batch reads as opposed to individual reads?
Carl Beekhuizen: So I think that's where, like, a lot of the intuition of, like, oh yeah, it's probably worth just, like, fetching all the state, whether it gets mutated or not.
Carl Beekhuizen: Like, before the execution starts.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, I mean, IÉ
Jared Wasinger: I definitely agree that, É I would definitely say that, like, I haven't benchmarked reads. It appears that, É
Jared Wasinger: the work from eStorage and, and Poe, Poe, or Chen, sorry, I, I, it appears that they'veÉ.
Po: Okay, you can callÉ Or, let's say, byÉ
Po: Feminine name, yeah. Always my English name.
Jared Wasinger: Okay, okay. É Yeah, I mean, IÉ
Jared Wasinger: It's definitely worth exploring, yeah, for sure.
Jared Wasinger: I'd like to benchmark it, and IÉ and I intend to.
Carl Beekhuizen: Okay, fantastic.
Carl Beekhuizen: Yeah, I think that'sÉ that there's, like, so much here that it's like, oh yeah, there could be one trade-off here, or one trade-off in another way, and it's like, benchmarks, I think, are the only way of answering these questions.
Toni WahrstŠtter: WhichÉ which exact benchmarks are you thinking of here, Charit? So, which benchmarks would youÉ because this should be something, like, very simÉ very simple to do, right?
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, so I would just implement theÉ
Jared Wasinger: I would implement reads, and then I wouldÉ
Jared Wasinger: I would benchmark them against SilaMainnet as a start.
Jared Wasinger: AndÉ
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, I mean, just batch loading the red storage slots up front, and see what kind of performanceÉ see what the results are.
Jared Wasinger: I mean, yeah, like I said, there's some interplay with, like, the state root computation, so implementing it isÉ
Jared Wasinger: I mean, it's not very complex, butÉ
Jared Wasinger: There's definitelyÉ yeah, I mean, it, it, É
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, just benchmarking against sila-mainnet and seeing ifÉ
Jared Wasinger: We can fiddle around with the implementation toÉ ToÉ yield performance gains?
Karim T.: I think it will also depend on theÉ who we implement theÉ
Karim T.: the block processing, because I said if we want also to compute the stage route from the beginning, we'll have also to batchÉ
Karim T.: Or try to read the intermediate node of the tree in order to compute the state root.
Karim T.: If you have also two batches the read.
Karim T.: So we'll have a lot of things to read at the beginning of the block. I feel that
Karim T.: It would be maybe better if we can mixÉ
Karim T.: between I.O. and CPU, so as I said, if we are running all of the transactions at the same time, sometimes we have I.O, and during I.O, we can run something else, any VML code or something like that, but if we do all of the batch at the beginning, we just wait at the beginning of the block to finish all of the I.O,
Karim T.: And, I don't know if it will be better or not just asking like that.
Karim T.: And thinking about that.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, I think it's a fair comment. I think we only find it out if we do some benchmarks andÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: And then we see, in the end, it's, it's, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: It's, like, the absolute time it takes to execute the whole block. Doesn't matter, if we do it up front or during execution.
Toni WahrstŠtter: So yeah, would beÉ I think we just need some benchmarks at this point.
Toni WahrstŠtter: to figure it out. Would be great if we can even get them from multiple clients to just have some more certainty onÉ on that decision.
Po: Yeah, extorted.
Po: Yeah.
Po: All theÉ generate the sales, theÉ
Po: Duh.
Po: Sorry, That's why IÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I, I think, I think we can't really hear you, Paul.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I think your mic has a problem.
Po: Okay, so is itÉ is it okay now?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Try it again?
Po: Okay, so I think I will have toÉ Transfer Mac.
Toni WahrstŠtter: No worry. Perfect.
Toni WahrstŠtter: É right.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I think we canÉ we can end that topic, regarding REITs, and at this point, I think at this point, we agree weÉ we need toÉ we need some more data.
Toni WahrstŠtter: To figure it out.
Toni WahrstŠtter: So I would say let's move on to the next agenda point, which is Rahul, telling us something about the testing efforts going on, and also Felipe is on the call. Would be great to hear his perspective on updates from him, too.
raxhvl: Hey, so I'm gonna quickly go over some updates on the testing front.
raxhvl: Give you some updates on the progress, give you a brief overview of how the test works on the record.
raxhvl: And then, a couple of housekeeping items.
raxhvl: So, É
raxhvl: The test mainly depends on two repositories. One is EAST, which is like a Python test testing framework.
raxhvl: And we have EALS, which is, like, a Python implementation of the spec.
raxhvl: We have both of tools working now.
raxhvl: We're currently trying a basic, set of tests, about 5 test cases.
raxhvl: And reviewing how that, It's been executed.
raxhvl: Once we are confident with that, we'll do a small release where, as clients, you guys can just start integrating
raxhvl: These tests as part of your development cycle.
raxhvl: And then, we'll keep on, working on more complex tests later.
raxhvl: Yeah, so Felipe is, like, doing, É Doing the integration testing now.
raxhvl: He's on the call to, like, give you an overview of how the test works under the hood.
raxhvl: Over to you, Chandita.
felipe: Yeah, sure. So right now there'sÉ
felipe: As Rahul mentioned, there's, there's the spec side.
felipe: Written in Python and the testing side as well. So, what I did, was some work trying to bridge, Tony's PR on the spec side with Rahul's on the testing side.
felipe: And, we got, got it working throughÉ
felipe: There were just some changes to your PR, Tony, to just pass things through the T8N tool, the transition tool that's talking across the testing and the specs.
felipe: And so, basically I got this working, we do have,
felipe: some of the basic tests Rahul is working on.
felipe: Right now, I'm figuring out how to make the developer experience a little better for adding some complex test cases and some invalid checks.
felipe: But as it's working, you know, this is, like, a general flow of East here. Transactions are sent over to the specs to fill.
felipe: these fixturesÉ eels is the specs in this case. They receive the block, they willÉ
felipe: build the block access list, and they pass it back. So weÉ what we pass back to the testing right now is the hash and the header.
felipe: and the ROP encoded, É Block access list from the specs.
felipe: What we do on the testing side is we define some smaller subset of the block access list that we care about for the test.
felipe: Some of these tests will have the full subset, right? Or it'll be, like, a full check on the valve that's returned.
felipe: But sometimes we only care about certain things, and so we do perform this check, but we also rehash the full, access list and check it against the hash in the header, so we always have this double check.
felipe: On the testing side.
felipe: And, yeah, Rahul, is there one more slide?
felipe: Yes, perfect.
felipe: And soÉ
felipe: Here, this is basically, like, once this fixture is filled with the specs, and this is a common flow for the testing as well.
felipe: This can be consumed by clients overÉ
felipe: consume engine, and so this just kind of shows, the flow there as well. But that'sÉ those are the updates on my side.
felipe: I doÉ I do actually have, initial implementation of theÉ of this, like, more complex, model structure, to start working on the invalid tests, andÉ and I didÉ
felipe: Write a couple invalid tests yesterday, but that's still a work in progress, but it does seem to be working well at the moment.
raxhvl: Thanks, Felipe.
raxhvl: Another thing that we noticed was, there areÉ
raxhvl: There are some creative tests, thatÉ that comes from that.
raxhvl: But they're often lost in Discord messages and GitHub issues.
raxhvl: So we're trying to aggregate that, as part of the report itself.
raxhvl: Into a Markdown file. This is, like, a structured Markdown file, whichÉ
raxhvl: Goes over, the goal of the test, the setup that is required, and the assertion that we're trying to make.
raxhvl: So, if you guys have any, any test cases in mind, I'd suggest.
raxhvl: Making a PR to this, this, background files.
raxhvl: And, we can probablyÉ Use that to make discussions, give focus updates, and for other high-level
raxhvl: Activity on the test cases.
raxhvl: É
raxhvl: We also are using this Markdown file along with the test case to integrate into Hive, which is like an integration framework which talks to all the clients.
raxhvl: É To create, like, an adoption dashboard.
raxhvl: This is what it looks like.
raxhvl: So, this pulls in the data from the markdown file in a way that's easier to read.
raxhvl: É for people to understand what's happening under the hood.
raxhvl: It also fills in the Python test against each client using pipes.
raxhvl: And then shows an update, on to our matrix here.
raxhvl: This runs on a CI server, É
raxhvl: And this is how it looks. You can tap on a test to see what exactly it's testing.
raxhvl: AndÉ yeah.
raxhvl: Obviously, there's a link toÉ to the background file for you guys to create a PR.
raxhvl: Yes.
raxhvl: That's all from us, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Awesome.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Thank you very much.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Both of you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, I posted, I posted your Markdown file, the link to it, in the chat.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Would be great if client devs, every time they come up with a new edge case.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Cannot do a PR against it.
Toni WahrstŠtter: We're already in the Discord I saw yesterday, I think, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: Can't find the message right now, but I think we already stumbled across a few edge cases where certain clients,
Toni WahrstŠtter: would have put that, certain address into the block lab access list, while others wouldn't have.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And in the end, I think we just need a lot of those test cases, too.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Get to a clean implementation.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Right, finally, I just wanted to ask clients about progress. It would be nice if client teams could just quickly give a little bit of an update where they are, what they think, about the EAP, and if there are any blockers or anything where we could help.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Maybe we can start withÉ with you, Jared.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, soÉ we actually have our first, review call on the PR tomorrow.
Jared Wasinger: SoÉ Hmm.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, from my side, not much right now, but maybe that will change after tomorrow, soÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Cool, thanks.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Is there someone from Besu here?
Karim T.: Yes, but maybe, É You can talk, Marieu.
mirgee: Yeah, sure, soÉ Amen.
mirgee: So in this event, we, we have implemented a degree of protocol support for BLs.
mirgee: É É
mirgee: But we still, we still need to update the engineering PI, and it's possible that we haven't, É
mirgee: incorporated, like, the spec changes. The PR has been open for, for
mirgee: What about the month with little changes?
mirgee: And it's possible that we are mishandling some of the edge cases.
mirgee: For example, I'm aware that We are omitting theÉ
mirgee: system contracts from BLs completely for the moment.
mirgee: É we've been testing against the bowel analysis, report and getting good results there.
mirgee: Was that worth?
mirgee: Yeah, but, É the PR has been blocked onÉ
mirgee: Some issues, but, otherwise, otherwiseÉ É
mirgee: That'sÉ that'sÉ I think that'sÉ that's our status.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Awesome, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Is there an update from someone at Aragon?
Mark Holt: Yeah, hi, it's Mark Holt here. I'm doing the BAL implementation at Aragon.
Mark Holt: Status is, I'm just starting, soÉ
Mark Holt: I'mÉ probably by the end of this week, I'll have an estimate of,
Mark Holt: how long it'll take to get to something that's working.
Mark Holt: I think we're just in the middle of merging. We've got aÉ we've got a parallel execution engine that we've been working on for some time, which is just going into main.
Mark Holt: So, I think the work to support, BAL is going to be just integrating the engine API and making sure that the data structures that we've got
Mark Holt: É essentially a mappable.
Mark Holt: Which, looking at the spec, I think is a relatively straightforward process.
Mark Holt: So, I mean, if it goes well, probably a couple of weeks will be in-dev testing, I would guess. If it goes badly, probably 3 or 4 weeks.
Mark Holt: I think is where we are.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, just to directly address, Karim's comment, about, that it would be nice to have a configuration ready for the first DevNet, especially decide on things like, do we want to put reads in there or not?
Toni WahrstŠtter: I would say right now the ERP is still, like, with reads, so I would still stick to having the reads included for now.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But, yeah, we can still, as said, as soon as we have some benchmarkÉ benchmarks, we can take a final decision.
Toni WahrstŠtter: I hope that we get the benchmarks before we get closer to a definite, so that we have the benchmarks rather soon, so that we can decide.
Toni WahrstŠtter: on that earlier.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, thank you, Mark. Is there anyone from REF here?
Soubhik: Hello, we're currentlyÉ
Soubhik: working on the engine API changes. Just today, we have done the new version for payload structure.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Awesome, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Did youÉ did you start with the engine API, or whichÉ of which part did you start there?
Soubhik: No, no. We have implemented the reads and write storage part already. We areÉ
Soubhik: We're currently recording both the reads and writes.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Thanks.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Do we have someone from Nethermind?
Marc: Yeah, hello. So, I've started prototyping, block access lists in Nethermind.
Marc: So far, I've been focusing on the, sort of, construction part, which has progressed pretty well, so the, sort of, construction and serialization.
Marc: And the way I decided to sort of approach it is to split it into two PRs, so there's the one which is, like, the construction, and then the other part is actually using the block access list, so all of the kind of parallelization aspect.
Marc: And I haven't really, É
Marc: worked on that part of it as much, and it seems like it will be significantly more, kind of complex.
Marc: ButÉ
Marc: the way I kind of understand it from the spec, it does seem quite logical to split it into those parts, because you could almost justÉ
Marc: Do the construction without necessarily leveraging everything, so that does seem to give us a little bit of, É
Marc: kind of flexibility there in terms of scheduling. I'm not sure if anyone else has approached it that way. É
Marc: But yeah, that's it for now.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Great, thank you.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, if there's nothing else that we want to discuss today, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: we can end the call. This was basically everything we had on the agenda. I note that we still need to do the benchmarking to decide upon
Toni WahrstŠtter: Do we want to include the reads or not? Or not the reads, but the state locations? This is kind ofÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: The same here.
Toni WahrstŠtter: And, yeah, and then we can discuss about the first definite. I think GEF and Biso might be the first clients thatÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: Might be ready.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But yeah, as the EAP is not that big, would be cool to get a Defnet, to get to a DEFNET as soon as possible.
Jared Wasinger: SoÉ
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, I guess, yeah, based on Carl's comment earlier, I personally kind of lean towards keeping reads in until we can demonstrate worst-case performance, which isn'tÉ
Jared Wasinger: trivial, so weÉ it would be nice to keep those in until we can set up some kind of, like, attack net where we spin up a bunch of these, like.
Jared Wasinger: Worst case, blocks without reads.
Jared Wasinger: Sorry, thatÉ I just realized that didn't make sense. I want to evaluate, like, what the worst-case performance is without having the reads before we decide whether or not to remove them.
Jared Wasinger: So, yeah.
Jared Wasinger: At least, yeah.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yep, that's fair.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect. Yeah, the ERP as it stands today, still includes the reads, so I think we just leave it as, as that, andÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: then we can still decide at some point if we want to remove them or not, but forÉ as a default, I would suggest we keep them for now.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Let's seeÉ.
Marc: JustÉ.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Your hand, yeah.
Marc: Yeah, I just had one quick question. So, I saw on the agenda something about RLP versus SSZ. I've gone with implementing RLP, butÉ and I kind ofÉ it seemed like last ACD
Marc: that was agreed upon, but I just want to check, are we kind of all in agreement that we're going to use that?
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, so just to summarize onÉ this was on all Cardiff's call, I think, last week, the majorityÉ I think most people wereÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: So most people didn't have a strong opinion.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But it seemed like theÉ the less complex way would be to just go with RLP and not use the ERP to introduce a newÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah.
Toni WahrstŠtter: to introduce, SSC.
Toni WahrstŠtter: This is kinda, also the default that is now in the EAP. I think we have some broad consensus on that.
Toni WahrstŠtter: But I'm happy to discuss that, if anyone else wants to.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, defend SSC.
Marc: Yeah, I mean, I think ROP makes sense to me.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Yeah, there were some pros and cons for both, like, SSC with smaller, more compact proofs.
Toni WahrstŠtter: might have some, advantages there too, but RLP, in the end, it's smaller, so we save, like, 10%, 5-10%, É
Toni WahrstŠtter: on the size, which is negligible, but still, and it's just known, so all clients have, codebases with RLP, and it, likeÉ
Toni WahrstŠtter: That's complex.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Perfect.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Boom.
Toni WahrstŠtter: Thank you very much, and see you in two weeks at the next breakout call.
Marc: It is, butÉ.
Jared Wasinger: Yeah, buddy.